Edgar Rice Burroughs papers, 1875-1950
UCLA Library Special Collections
Edgar Rice Burroughs papers
Bulk, 1920-1945
1875-1950
2263
UCLA Library Special Collections
12.6 linear feet (9 record cartons, 4 document boxes, 2 flat storage boxes, 1 shoebox)
This collection documents the activities and political opinions of Edgar Rice Burroughs. Burroughs was a California-based science fiction and fantasy author. An outspoken political conservative, he created iconic characters like Tarzan and John Carter. He was also the oldest US wartime correspondent in World War II, and advocated for Japanese Americans near the end of the war. The collection spans from 1875 to 1950, and chronicles Burroughs’ time in California, Hawaii, and the greater South Pacific.
Conditions Governing Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance through our electronic paging system using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Some of the correspondence in Series 1 and 3 is torn or frayed on the edges. The audio cassettes and video cassette in Series 2 are of unknown quality and have not been digitally copied.
COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 7745478
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Purchase, 2014.
Biography/History
Edgar Rice Burroughs was born in Chicago, Illinois on September 1, 1875 to Civil War veteran Major George Tyler Burroughs and Mary Evaline (Zieger) Burroughs. He graduated from the Michigan Military Academy in 1895, but failed the entrance exam for the United States Military Academy (West Point). He became an enlisted soldier with the 7th US Cavalry in Fort Grant, Arizona Territory. In 1897, he was diagnosed with a heart problem and honorably discharged. Burroughs married Emma Hulbert in January 1900. They had three children: Joan (b. 1908), Hulbert (b. 1909), and John (b. 1913).
Burroughs began to write fiction in 1911. His first story, “Under the Moons of Mars,” was serialized in the February to July 1912 issues of, under the pseudonym Norman Bean. Tarzan of the Apes was published in October 1912, and quickly became a cultural sensation. Burroughs exploited the Tarzan brand through a comic strip, movies, radio programs, and merchandise, to great success. In either 1915 or 1919, Burroughs purchased a large ranch north of Los Angeles, California, which he named “Tarzana.” The citizens of the community that formed around the ranch adopted the town name Tarzana in 1927. In 1923, he set up his own company, Edgar Rice Burroughs, Inc. and began printing his own books through the 1930s. He also began Burroughs-Tarzan Productions, an independent film studio.
Edgar Rice Burroughs divorced Emma Hulbert in 1934. In 1935 he married former actress Florence Gilbert Dearholt, the ex-wife of his friend, Ashton Dearholt. Burroughs adopted the Dearholts’ two children. The couple divorced in 1942.
Burroughs was in Honolulu at the time of the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor. He applied for a reporting post, and became one of the oldest U.S. war correspondents during World War II. Burroughs was a political conservative, suspicious of Japanese Americans, and a strong critic of Roosevelt’s New Deal politics. Despite this, he advocated against the internment and deportation of Japanese Americans during and after the war, arguing such actions went against the “Americanism” that made the nation great.
After the war ended, Burroughs moved back to California, and died of a heart attack on March 19, 1950. He wrote almost 80 novels, including the Tarzan series, the Barsoom series, and the Pellucidar series. He is buried in Tarzana, Los Angeles County. He was inducted into the Science Fiction Hall of Fame in 2003.
Scope and Content
This collection documents the activities and political opinions of Edgar Rice Burroughs, the California-based science fiction and fantasy author whose iconic characters include John Carter and Tarzan.
The collection spans from 1875 to 1950, with the bulk of materials coming from the 1920s-1940s, and is in chronological order. It chronicles Burroughs’ time in California, Hawaii, and the broader South Pacific. In addition to professional materials, including correspondence, press clippings, unpublished manuscripts, and reporting notebooks, the collection contains a large quantity of personal material, such as letters to and from Burroughs, correspondence among his children, and reflections on his time as a war correspondent during World War II.
Some of the significant topics represented in these files are: publishing concerns; innovations in media and advertising; the Great Depression; the New Deal; local police; World War II; foreign relations; wartime journalism; the internment of Japanese Americans; wartime rationing; the growth of the science fiction and fantasy genres; and censorship. The collection documents Burroughs’ success as an author and businessman; his political conservatism; his advocacy for Japanese American rights; and his wartime reporting; as well as his observational humor, close bond with his children, and thoughts on the entertainment industry.
Materials are largely textual, comprising correspondence, financial and legal material, clippings, publications, and related printed matter. Among other formats are photographs, negatives, and a small number of artifacts such as a video cassette, nine audio cassettes, and ephemera.
Organization and Arrangement
The records are arranged in four series. The contents of each series are arranged either chronologically or by type.
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Binders 1893-1950
Series 2: Photographs and Other Media 1875-1950
Series 3: Manuscripts and Notes 1908-1947
Series 4: Books 1875-1964
Related Material
Collection of Material about Japanese American Internment (Collection 131). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Collection of Material about World War II (Collection 502). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Burroughs, Edgar Rice, 1875-1950 -- Archives; Novelists, American--20th century--Archives.
Container List
- Series 1: Binders., 1893-1950.
  Scope and Content
  Series comprises primarily the personal and professional correspondence of Edgar Rice Burroughs, compiled into binders. Records pertain to Burroughs’ time in California, Hawaii, and the broader South Pacific. Other materials include promotional materials, financial records, internal memos, press clippings, and photographs. These records pertain to the growth of the Tarzan brand, Burroughs’ personal life and political opinions, and his experiences as a wartime correspondent.
  Organization and Arrangement
  Resources arranged chronologically; original binders retained.
  - Binder One., March 31, 1893 - September 22, 1925. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Contains correspondence from beginnings of Edgar Rice Burroughs Inc. Items of Interest: Autographed promotional materials, membership with The Breakfast Club, Burroughs’ thoughts on Roman Catholicism, references to UCLA, and letters from Emma Hulbert Burroughs.
  - Binder Two., February 22, 1926 - December 3, 1927. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Binder Three., January 24, 1928 - December 27, 1929. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Binder Four., January 8, 1930 - December 28, 1931. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Binder Five., January 7, 1932 - December 6, 1932. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Contains Burroughs' correspondence with his children on their professional and artistic pursuits and correspondence on how best to market the Tarzan brand. Items of Interest: Discussion of Hulbert’s military camp training, autographed promotional materials, and letters from Emma Hulbert Burroughs.
  - Binder Six., January 18, 1933 - August 16, 1933. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Binder Seven., September 9, 1933 - November 13, 1933. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Binder Eight., January 4, 1934 - December 28, 1934. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Binder Nine., January 4, 1935 - December 27, 1935. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Chronicles the growing Tarzan brand. Items of Interest: Contains personal correspondence regarding the police altercation with Burroughs' eldest son, Hulbert (“Hully”) Burroughs, and the Burroughs family's complaint against the LAPD (including op-ed to the Los Angeles Times); also contains Burroughs’ thoughts on Franklin and Eleanor Roosevelt and on the Republican Party.
  - Binder Ten., January 2, 1936 - December 25, 1936. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Binder Eleven., January 2, 1937 - December 27, 1937. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Binder Twelve., January 4, 1938 - December 24, 1938. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Binder Thirteen., January 6, 1939 - December 25, 1939. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Contains personal and professional correspondence detailing Burroughs' first and second divorce, his journey to Hawaii, and the beginning of World War II. Items of Interest: Continuing correspondence on the incident between LAPD and Hulbert (“Hully”) Burroughs, Burroughs' discovery of Tarzan translations into native Hawaiian, Burroughs' 1940 visit to Pearl Harbor, Hulbert’s time in the armed forces, and jokes about wartime censorship.
  - Binder Fourteen., March 1, 1940 - December 29, 1940. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Binder Fifteen., January 3, 1941 - December 31, 1941. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Binder Sixteen., January 29, 1942 - December 31, 1942. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Binder Seventeen., January 16, 1943 - January 31, 1944. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Chronicles Burroughs' beginning research into the "Japanese Question" of what to do with Japanese Americans during after the war. Items of Interest: Examples of anti-Japanese rhetoric, Burroughs' thoughts on New Deal policies, an elaboration on his vision of "Americanism," references to the Johnny Roselli case, and notes on Burroughs' experiences as a columnist and wartime correspondent.
  - Binder Eighteen., February 7, 1944 - April 29, 1944. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Binder Nineteen., May 3, 1944 - July 31, 1944. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Binder Twenty., August 1, 1944 – October 30, 1944. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Binder Twenty One., November 3, 1944 - February 10, 1945. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Chronicles Burroughs' ambivalent advocacy efforts for Japanese Americans and his worsening health. Items of Interest: Reference to article "What Price Intolerance," correspondence on censoring Tarzan's G-string, correspondence between Burroughs and the Japanese American Citizens League, correspondence with Jean O’Hara on her book Honolulu Harlot about vice conditions, and correspondence on surrender of Germany and Japan.
  - Binder Twenty Two., February 10, 1945 - April 29, 1945. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Binder Twenty Three., May 1, 1945 - July 31, 1945. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Binder Twenty Four., August 1, 1945 - November 30, 1945. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Binder Twenty Five., December 1, 1945 - January 29, 1946. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Chronicles Burroughs' worsening health and the effects of World War II. Items of Interest: Discussion of wartime rationing and Burroughs' references on the decolonization of the British Empire.
  - Binder Twenty Six., February 9, 1946 - May 31, 1946. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Binder Twenty Seven., June 8, 1946 - December 17, 1946. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Binder Twenty Eight., January 3, 1947 - June 2, 1947. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Binder Twenty Nine., June 3, 1947 - December 31, 1947. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Burroughs' discharge from the army and return to California. Items of Interest: Correspondence with and about Minna Diack, the widow of Charles Diack who published Burroughs’ novels in German; references to heart condition and army discharge.
  - Binder Thirty., January 5, 1948 - June 22, 1948. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Binder Thirty One., July 21, 1948 - March 19, 1950. (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Series 2: Photographs and Other Media., 1875-1950.
  Series comprises photographs of Edgar Rice Burroughs and his family, promotional materials (photographs, lobby cards, and) for the Tarzan films, video recordings of the Burroughs family in America and Hawaii 1939-1940, and audio recordings of the Tarzan radio program, 1951-1952.
  Resources arranged by media type.
  Conditions Governing Access
  COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - The New Adventures of Tarzan Promotional Materials., 1935. (Box 9)
  - Tarzan and the Green Goddess Promotional Materials., 1938. (Box 10)
  - Cassette Audio Recording: Tarzan Radio Program, "Tarzen and the Killer," "Jungle Legacy"., 1951. (Box 11)
  - Cassette Audio Recording: Tarzan Radio Program, "Tarzen, Lord of the Jungle: Congo Murder," "Across a Continent"., circa 1951. (Box 11)
  - Cassette Audio Recording: Tarzan Radio Program, "Tarzen, Lord of the Jungle: Tarzen and the Lypagor," "Tarzen and the Hot Rod Kid"., circa 1951. (Box 11)
  - Cassette Audio Recording: Tarzan Radio Program, "Tarzen and the Long Journey," "Tarzen and the Decoy"., circa 1951. (Box 11)
  - Cassette Audio Recording: Tarzan Radio Program, "Tarzen and the Long Journey," "Tarzen and the Decoy"., circa 1951. (Box 11)
  - Cassette Audio Recording: Tarzan Radio Program, "Tarzen and the Coward," "The Female of the Species"., 1951. (Box 11)
  - Cassette Audio Recording: Tarzan Radio Program, "Gold Coast Robbery," "The Siren of Omduh Mara"., 1952. (Box 11)
  - Cassette Audio Recording: Tarzan Radio Program, "End of the World," "Jungle Smoke"., circa 1952. (Box 11)
  - Cassette Audio Recording: Tarzan Radio Program, "Killer at Large," "None So Blind"., circa 1952. (Box 11)
  - Cassette Audio Recording: Tarzan Radio Program, "Life or Death," "Jungle Heat"., 1952. (Box 11)
  - VHS Video Recording: "Film by and of Edgar Rice Burroughs, America and Hawaii"., 1939-1940. (Box 11)
  - Photograph Negatives: Boating., 1933. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Photograph Negatives: Photos of Burroughs., 1900-1935. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Photograph Negatives: Burroughs family., 1920-1940. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Photograph Negatives: Family at Tarzana Ranch., 1919-1932. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Photograph Negatives: Family trips., 1926-1933. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Photograph Negatives: Illinois., 1915-1933. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Photograph Negatives: Malibu home., 1932-1934. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Photograph Negatives: Tarzan set., 1919-1922. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Photograph Negatives: Unlabeled., undated. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Photograph Negatives: Unlabeled, people in costume., undated. (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Photograph Negatives: Misc.., 1895-1989. (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Photograph Prints: Burroughs and family in uniform., undated. (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Photograph Prints: Personal., circa early 1900s. (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Photographs and Promotional Materials., 1875-1950. (Box 13, Folder 1-5)
    Contains head shots, set photos, family photographs, souvenir tickets, and photo negatives.
- Series 3: Manuscripts and Notes., 1908-1947.
  Series comprises personal and professional correspondence before and during World War II, press and magazine clippings, reporter’s notes and war reports, a daily diary (1946), a financial ledger, ephemera, and manuscripts for Burroughs’ wartime “Laugh It Off” column in the Honolulu Star-Bulletin, his coverage of Japanese Americans in Hawaii, You Lucky Girl (unpublished, 1927), and The War Chief (1927).
  Resources arranged by type of work or writing.
  - Personal: Better Homes and Gardens Containing Article on Burroughs Home., 1931. (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Personal: Book of the Month Club Issues and Requests., 1945-1946. (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Personal: Correspondence and Sketches, Copies., 1900s-1940s. (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Personal: Correspondence with Joan Burroughs., 1940s. (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Personal: Daily Diary., 1946. (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Personal: Financial Ledger Documenting Personal Expenses., 1939-1946. (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Personal: Handwritten Notes., 1942-1943. (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Personal: Legal and Medical Documents., 1940-1945. (Box 14, Folder 13)
    Contains social security card, prescriptions and doctor’s medical notes, certificates and bills of sale, insurance receipts, and county clerk certification of Burroughs’ birth records.
  - Personal: Press Clippings for Personal and Research Purposes., 1947. (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Published Articles: “Entertainment is Fiction’s Purpose” in Writer’s Digest., 1930. (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Published Articles: “Laugh It Off” Column for Honolulu Star-Bulletin., 1940s. (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Published Articles: “Laugh It Off” Correspondence., 1940s. (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Published Novel: The War Chief Index and Outline., 1927. (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Published Play: You Lucky Girl Manuscript., 1927. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - World War II Writings: War Reports for Businessmen's Military Training Corps, Radio KGMB, and United Press., 1942-1945. (Box 15, Folders 1-4)
    Burroughs became the public relations officer for the BMTC, a civilian home defense organization, in 1942. The creation of the BMTC was partly in response to the fear among many whites on the island that the Japanese Hawaiians (Nisei) would rise up and fight for Japan. Over the course of his reports, Burroughs shifts from suspicion of Japanese Americans to frustration at the lack of support and respect they were given from the armed forces.
  - World War II Writings: Military Cipher., 1942. (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - World War II Writings: Manuscripts and Correspondence Regarding Wartime Reporting., 1942-1944. (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - World War II Writings: Wartime Correspondence and Research., 1943-1945. (Box 15, Folders 5-7)
  - World War II Writings: "Japanese Question" Correspondence and Research., 1943-1945. (Box 15, Folders 10-11)
    Press clippings and materials regarding Emergency Services and the treatment of Japanese Americans during wartime for research purposes, and correspondence regarding Burroughs’ reporting on the question of what to do with people of Japanese descent after the war.
- Series 4: Books., 1875-1964.
  Series comprises books written or used by Edgar Rice Burroughs, 1875-1964. It encompasses research books, a dictionary, a thesaurus, books by Burroughs’ family and friends, and books by Edgar Rice Burroughs.
  Books arranged chronologically.
  Physical Characteristics
  Thesaurus (pub. 1875) is in very delicate condition.
  - Thesaurus., 1875. (Box 16)
  - Jungle Trails and Jungle People by Caspar Whitney., 1905. (Box 16)
  - The Squaw Man by Julie Opp Faversham., 1906. (Box 16)
  - Memoirs of a War Bride by Mary Evaline Burroughs., 1914. (Box 16)
  - An Auto-Biography (2) by Edgar Rice Burroughs., 1917. (Box 16)
  - Pearls and Savages by Captain Frank Hurley., 1924. (Box 16)
  - The Autocrats of the Breakfast Club by Frederick Courtenay Barber., 1930s. (Box 16)
  - Webster’s Collegiate Dictionary., 1943. (Box 16)
  - The War Chief by Edgar Rice Burroughs., 1964. (Box 16)